<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Plain dealer an essay wherein are some remarks upon Mr. Thomas Long, but more particularly upon Dr. Hollingworth's book where the character of King Charles the first is inserted from the declaration of Mr. Alexander Henderson, which book he calls A further defence of the Kings holy book &amp;c.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1692</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 30 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A54970</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P2349</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R26227</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">09398326</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 09398326</idno>
            <idno type="VID">42957</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A54970)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 42957)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1314:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Plain dealer an essay wherein are some remarks upon Mr. Thomas Long, but more particularly upon Dr. Hollingworth's book where the character of King Charles the first is inserted from the declaration of Mr. Alexander Henderson, which book he calls A further defence of the Kings holy book &amp;c.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>16 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1692.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Trinity College Library, Cambridge University.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Hollingworth, Richard, 1639?-1701. --  Character of King Charles I.</term>
               <term>Henderson, Alexander, 1583?-1646. --  Declaration of Mr. Alexand. Henderson.</term>
               <term>Charles --  I, --  King of England, 1600-1649.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:42957:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:42957:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>The Plain Dealer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>AN ESSAY, Wherein are ſome REMARKS upon Mr. <hi>THOMAS LONG;</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But more particularly upon Dr. <hi>HOLLINGWORTH's Book.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>WHERE The Character of King <hi>CHARLES</hi> the Firſt is inſerted from the Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of Mr. <hi>Alexander Henderſon:</hi> Which Book he calls, <hi>A further Defence of the King's Holy Book.</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed in the Year 1692.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="essay">
            <pb facs="tcp:42957:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:42957:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>THE</hi> Plain Dealer.</head>
            <p>THere has been a vile Buſtle between one <hi>Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chard Hollingworth</hi> Doctor, and an unknown Author, in two or three Anſwers to ſome Papers came abroad under the Name of <hi>Lieutenant General Ludlow.</hi> The great Struggle is, Whether <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt wrote that Book entituled <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or was the Martyr aſſerted in the two laſt Reigns, under <hi>Charles</hi> the 2d; and that moſt Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious, Merciful, Brave and Wife Prince, the late King <hi>James</hi> of Bleſſed Memory,<note n="*" place="margin">In Mr. <hi>Hender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi>'s Character of
<hi>Ch.</hi> I. pag. 3. in Dr. <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingworth</hi>'s Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marks.</note> two Princes the hopefulleſt that ever were in theſe ingrate Nations. The Doctor, like a Politick Clergy-man, to ſay no more of him, has took the ſtrongeſt Side; and I muſt ſay, the Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man that provoked him, muſt be a bold Man, when<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever ſince Sixty, (the Time we date the Proſperity and Glory of theſe Nations, when Luxury ceaſed; when one of thoſe hopeful Princes already mentioned, exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plary in Piety, Vertue, Religion, Chaſtity and Fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gality, influenced all about him) a Law was on his Side, a Man's Head was the Price of but Whiſpering againſt,<note place="margin">The Anniver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary preaching up of the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrdom of <hi>Ch.</hi> I.</note> of which the Clergy (to whom the Doctor is related, and who never fail to flatter Power) were the Interpreters. It ſignfies not much to our preſent Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs, <pb n="4" facs="tcp:42957:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>(though the Church-of-<hi>England</hi>-men think them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Long</hi> in his Preface, is in ſuch a ſury up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it, that when he reads it in his calmer Temper, he'l bluſh to find his grey Head guilty of ſuch intemperance.</note> ruffled to their undoing) though in both, with ſubmiſſion, all the Arguments ſeem againſt the Doctor, whether
<hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt wrote that Book, or was the Martyr; nor ſhould either have made me ſet Pen to Paper, had not the Doctor's indirect and malicious courſe to have his Book gain Credit, and the baſe Treatment he and Mr. <hi>Long</hi> make the Gentleman, whoſe Name (and they know it) without his privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty (though he ought not to think himſelf affronted at it) the Author there makes uſe of,
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> been the oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion. As to the malicious' part of which, ſhould I make Remarks of all the Doctor writes, I ſhould grow tedious, and as Impertinent as our Clergy-man; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I ſhall only obſerve the Doctor's <hi>Darling,</hi> his <hi>laſt Anſwer,</hi> for which I expect Cannonading with double Shot, if the Doctor out of his languiſhing Magazine has any left, <hi>to the vile Book,</hi> &amp;c. I proteſt it ſeems to me as ill-natured a Piece as any e're ſent abroad; and the Declaration in the Front the Doctor values ſo much, wrote by a Man highly diſobliged.</p>
            <p>For there, <hi>Pag.</hi> 3. Mr. <hi>Henderſon</hi>'s words are,
<q rend="margQuotes">That which we eſteem a God-like Kirk-Policy, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted by the Lord Chriſt and his Apoſtles, is no better to them than a kind of Slavery; and ſome do not ſtick to call it worſe than the Spaniſh Inquiſition; nay even the greateſt part of thoſe who invited us to aſſiſt them in it, and ſent hither their Commiſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, to induce us to enter into a ſolemn National Covenant for that Effect, having ſerved their Turn of us, to throw down the King, and the Prelatical Party, and to poſſeſs themſelves with the Supream Government both of Kirk and State, are now in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venting Evaſions to be rid of us; and to delude it, <pb n="5" facs="tcp:42957:3"/>ſome of them publiſhing openly in their Pulpits, and Print, that the Sacred Covenant was never intended for the Godly,
<hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </q> Was not the Doctor put to his laſt Stake, ſure he would never have in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerted the Character of King <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt, given by this Man, apparently diſguſted<note n="*" place="margin">Tho I have been lately in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed this Character ſaid to be
<hi>Hender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi>'s was not writ by <hi>him,</hi> but ſoiſted in by this, or ſuch a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother Author.</note>? In one place of his Books the Doctor expreſſes vehemently an averſion to <hi>Presbytery,</hi> and ſays,
<q rend="margQuotes">He never was a Presbyterian in his Life, and by God's Grace never will: for I neither liked the Principles of that Government, nor the Spirit of too many of that Party.</q> Yet the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor gives you a taſte of what he may be upon occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; for though he ſays, <hi>he will not be,</hi> &amp;c. he makes uſe of one of the<note n="†" place="margin">Ridgedeſt.</note> worſt of them to ſerve his Turn. And I am afraid, ſhould the Government once turn upon that Point, ſince the Doctor ſo profligately makes uſe of Presbyterian Prejudice, was it for his Turn, he would be perſwaded to be one of them; but whilſt it is not, I conclude with the Doctor, that he will love the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of the Church, and the Sweets of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and as he ſays, <hi>Pag.</hi> 22. what in him lies promote its true Intereſt, while he has a Tongue to ſpeak, or a Pen to write.</p>
            <p>But we will leave the Doctor to his Reſolution, and make ſome other Remarks may back our Opinion, that this laſt Piece of our reſolute Gentleman's has in it much of Malice and ill Nature; for, <hi>Pag.</hi> 15. he ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſts nothing will ſatisfy the Perſon he pretends to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, and his Party, but extirpating Monarchy, the Church, and all good Men: for there he ſays, barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly enough, <hi>the Ends of them are to deſtroy Church and State,</hi> and therefore not one word of the Vertues of this Prince I warrant you. But this is not the only rancor'd thing our good-natured
<hi>Anſwerer</hi> has ſubtilly <pb n="6" facs="tcp:42957:4"/>couched in this his notable Paper; for <hi>Pag.</hi> 17 and 18, taxing the Author of the <hi>Lewd Book,</hi> as the Doctor with his uſual Rhetorick calls it, for aſſerting that the Condeſcenſion of King <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt, in paſſing ſo many Bills the firſt Year of the Parliament, were no Favours, nor deſerved Thanks, he obſerves (for this Man and his Party muſt deſign againſt all Kings) ſuch an Aſſertion takes off all Obligations to their preſent Majeſties, and their Succeſſors, from the People, as to any future Acts of Grace they grant; <hi>for which,</hi> ſays he, <hi>he deſerves no Thanks from the Crown;</hi> and indeed, for which he ought to be looked upon as a down-right Enemy to the future Intercourſe and good Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding betwixt their Majeſties and their People, and hopes the ſaucy Aſſertion will be taken notice of. One may boldly aver here, was our good-natured Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor in Power, <hi>ſaying</hi> ſhould not gratify his Spleen; but thanks be to the humble Sphere of our Divine, though the Author has the <hi>Grinn,</hi> he remains out of the reach of <hi>Biting.</hi> Knowing little of the King's Book, though I may as well pretend to write againſt it, upon that little knowledg I have of it, as the Doctor does for it, having only ſeen under the Earl of <hi>Angle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſey</hi>'s own Hand, that King
<hi>Charles</hi> the Second, and King <hi>James</hi> when Duke of
<hi>York,</hi> denied it writ by their Father; which Dr. <hi>Walker</hi> has made out to all but thoſe that, like the Doctor and Mr. <hi>Long,</hi> will not be convinced. I intended by this Paper, only to ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign the Doctor's malicious Bitterneſs to the Author, and to the Gentleman his Book owes his Title to; but there are two things in it ſo down-right falſe, though aſſerted with the ſame Spirit of Confidence as runs through his whole Book, that I had been an Enemy to Truth, had they patted me: I ſhall incur Cenſure for <pb n="7" facs="tcp:42957:4"/>it, and come under the Doctor's unmannerly ſeventh <hi>Query,</hi> viz. <hi>That all are great</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">They muſt be Knaves and Fools, (to uſe our civil Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man's own words) that do nor, when the whole Nation then aſſembled in Parliament was of a contrary Opinion. This, I think, is anſwering one of his
<hi>Queries</hi> to the purpoſe. And a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny one may gueſs what Honour the Doctor has by the follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing eighth <hi>Query,</hi> who gives him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf the trouble of reading it.</note> 
               <hi>Fools, or deſigning Knaves, that believe any thing, the Libeller writes againſt King <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>One is, his aſſerting ſo boldly, that <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt began not that unhappy War with the Parliament; and mentions (<hi>Pag.</hi> 21.) the words of King <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt upon the Scaffold, as his Argument for it. It's Chriſtian-like to let the Aſhes of the Dead reſt: And heartily I wiſh, inſtead of raking therein, a Vail drawn over the Actions of that unfortunate Prince, might cauſe them never to be thought of more. But our <hi>bold Divine,</hi> ſhould we uſe more modeſty than he's ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with, upon miſtake, would preſently conclude the Advantage his, and bulkely, in a conceited Triumph, troubleſomely appear again. Therefore to do the Town a kindneſs (without unexampled Impudence) in hinder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it, it may be truly affirmed, That the Doctor <hi>ſhuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fles</hi> abominably, when he taxes for it, in the ſame Page, our Author; and that what the Doctor calls <hi>ſhuffing,</hi> is an apparent Truth. And the ſending the Crown-Jewels into <hi>Holland,</hi> (let our Doctor ſillily inſinuate never ſo much, that the Actions of Princes are above our reach, and ought not (as in the ſaid <hi>Pag.</hi> 21.) to be ſo narrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly pried into, and his <hi>dare ſays,</hi> &amp;c.) was infallibly the beginning of that War: for the Crown-Jewels were conveyed by the Queen into <hi>Holland</hi> in 1641, that with them, and the Aſſiſtance of the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> a ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient Party might be raiſed for the King. <hi>Whitlock</hi> (the Doctor in ſeveral parts of his Book ſeems ſo plauſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble with, being in this againſt him) probably will not be allowed this Truth, aſſerted in his <hi>Memoiers,</hi> p. 52.
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:42957:5"/>He farther tells you, <hi>Pag.</hi> 57. that a Ship of Ammu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition was taken; coming to the King from <hi>Holland;</hi> and that both the carrying the Crown-Jewels, and taking this Ship, was before the Parliament had voted an Army ſhould be raiſed. Several other Inſtances of the beginning the War on the King's Side, are there mentioned; the leaſt would convince any Man, but thoſe (bribed and biaſſed ever ſince Sixty, by the State, upon the 30th of <hi>January,</hi> with good Benefices) to ſay the contrary; and their Auditors, implicitly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenting to theſe thus intereſted and influenced-Men, who like theſe, telling a falſe thing too frequently, at laſt take it and tell it for true, and ſteadily believe it ſo. But let them go on with their Buffoonry, they can, I hope, do little hurt now; Time, and the ſad Effects of the laſt diſſolute Reigns, under the hopeful Branches of the Doctor's great and vertuous Prince the Martyr, has convinced many, and will more, the Government under him was not ſo regular as it ſhould be: And I am confident the time will come, though there are<note n="*" place="margin">The bringing back the late King <hi>James.</hi>
               </note> Deſigns to hinder it, poſſibly too by ſome of thoſe
<hi>Thirtieth-of-January-Men,</hi> when the Government will think it ſcandalous to celebrate that Day; and that none need to take pains to convince the World, that the Unfortunate <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt, was breaking through our <hi>Laws</hi> and <hi>Liberties</hi> in general; nor for his Credit in particular, that he both began that Unhappy War, and countenanced that Rebellion in <hi>Ireland.</hi> The excuſing him of which laſt, is the other of the two things in the Doctor's Book I have already told you in this Paper, is ſo apparently falſe; for which there are at hand ſuch Arguments, and convincing Reaſons, that our Doctor ought to be told, the World for the future, notwithſtanding the honeſt Account,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:42957:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>(mentioned <hi>Pag.</hi> 21.) he ſays he has given of himſelf, will have no great Opinion of his Modeſty or Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grity, nor wonder at the falſity of any thing comes abroad with our <hi>Clever Divine</hi>'s Name to it; ſome of which were ſo obvious, the moſt partial Writers of theſe Times cannot help taking notice of, careſſing and countenancing the Heads of that Rebellion long ☜ before it actually was ſo, none does or can excuſe, nor after the admitting and incouraging the Negotia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors of a Ceſſation; ſo fatal to <hi>Ireland,</hi> at a time when the whole Bent of his Arms, for the Good of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, ſhould have been for their Deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction,<note place="margin">Not only only <hi>Dunkirkers</hi> by their means, having the King's War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant for it, but Sir <hi>John Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nington,</hi> who commanded the King's Ships, had Orders for it.</note> admitting of their Counſels for the interception of Proviſions deſigned there, when the miſerable Neceſſities of that Place moſt wanted them; and alſo for the Seizing and Impriſoning the Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſengers of the Parliament, and taking their Money from them raiſed in the Countrey by Loans, intended for the Relief of that Afflicted Place, and converting it to other Uſes. But probably this neither reliſhing with our Doctor, he may, according to his honeſt E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducation and old Sincerity, be very plain with me, in the Language he treats the Gentleman he pretends to anſwer, and put this Paper among the ſcandalous Books (in this Clergy-man's Opinion) writ ſince the laſt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volution againſt Church and State, and with the utmoſt Effort of Malice; as in <hi>Pag.</hi> 13. of his Book invoke, the Arch-Biſhops, Biſhops, Nobility, Gentry, Clergy, and Commons of the Nation, for endeavouring with Trifles like theſe, to ſully the gloſſy Vertues of that Prince; and if I tell him, wherein is all the double-dealing in the World, of Letters under this Prince's own Hand, to the Marqueſs of <hi>Ormond</hi> for making <pb n="10" facs="tcp:42957:6"/>Peace with the Iriſh Rebels, ſome of which came over with Colonel <hi>Earnely</hi> to ſerve him, to bring that Army (which in the Iriſh Shambles had learn'd the Bloody Trade of cutting Throats) into <hi>England.</hi> Nay,<note place="margin">It is ſomething unhappy for our Doctor, that the Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man is yet alive that owns he returned the Money: He is a Perſon of Learning, Honeſty and Honour, and will be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved; I would name him, but have too great a value for him, to do it without his leave. I preſume we may have the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor as groſs againſt this, as the other Truths of his Martyr's Reign; if he is, this Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man has no inferior Pen to our Doctor, and will give him an Anſwer, and the Truth of that Affair.</note> if I tell him, and make it appear, which I can do, that Money was returned, by this Martyr, into <hi>Ireland,</hi> to ſome of the Heads of that Rebellion, he will have recourſe to his old Cant, rail at the Aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, give blackning Language, ſay, it's the <hi>old Leaven</hi> and Spirit makes me ſay all this; and. conclude, I have Deſigns upon Church and State, conjure them upon their Guard, and to erect a Gibbet imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately. But let this reviling Man go on, aſſerting his own integrity; Time has begun, and will pull off the Mask, and ſhow our mouthing Doctor, and ſome of that Tribe, in their Colours, when their Diſhoneſty, want of Morals and Humanity, will appear ſo plain, the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt Men (if ſuch there are) will bluſh to think they have been miſled ſo long. It is no eaſy matter, when a ſet of Men, for politick Ends, with full ſwing has beat the Pulpit for thirty Years, and more, upon one Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, to remove the Prejudice, for the moſt part, of an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>examining Nation, gained by ſuch means; and indeed nothing leſs than what was intended, altering Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, breaking the Laws, and enſlaving the Nation, could have done it: yet theſe Men juſtify, and, like the Doctor, cry up their Honeſty, when their whole Bent was for encouraging (as <hi>Laud,</hi> our Doctor's Saint and Biſhop, and others, Men of the ſame Principles, did the unhappy <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt) Arbitrary De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns. How ſupinely remiſs was <hi>Charles</hi> the Second,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:42957:6"/>upon their full Cry for <hi>Paſſive Obedience, Jure Divino, Kings can do no wrong;</hi> that <hi>the Kingdom was by Inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance; the People made for the King, not the King for the People;</hi> and <hi>that they were accountable to none for their Actions but God Almighty.</hi> Their Expreſſions upon theſe Subjects, (ſome of which as a taſte, though e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to nauſiate the Stomach of an honeſt Man) I have here from themſelves inſerted.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">I have not mentioned the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors, who, becauſe upon the extreams, which are ſeldom or never laſting, may be now (and I believe ſome of them are) of another Opinion.</note>That the Prince's Patent is from God; that no Accident or Occurrences, can diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve it to make us reſiſt, unleſs (which we are aſſured he will not) God himſelf ſhould revoke the Grant.</p>
            <p>The Church of <hi>England</hi> gives to all Princes the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premacy in their reſpective Dominions, as well over Spiritual as Temporal Perſons, in Sacred as well as Civil Cauſes: Which we count (ſpeaking of its Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers) not as an Act of Grace, or any baſe flattering of Authority, or fawning upon the Crown, but 'tis the expreſſion of a juſt Debt, and a bare Recognition of what is their undoubted Right, and what they always did enjoy.</p>
            <p>That they cannot be Supream, if <hi>Minor <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſis,</hi> and may be reſiſted in the tyrannical and exorbitant uſe of their Power.</p>
            <p>Theſe Arguments too often aſſerted, made the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy ſo abſolute, and the Nation in general ſo care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, that the Growth of
<hi>France,</hi> like to be the Ruin of <hi>Europe,</hi> was taken no notice of. The moſt <hi>ſauntring</hi> Prince that e're governed theſe Realms, magnified to Idolatry; and the meaneſt-ſpirited Prince, incapable both of Friendſhip and Valour, celebrated as the greateſt Hero, the greateſt Friend, when Popery was tiding in upon theſe Nations chiefly by his means.
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:42957:7"/>How, when ſome few Men in Parliament oppoſed it, by offering at a Bill of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion, did the Pulpit<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>One of our Churchmen, in a Sermon preached</hi> June 21.1685.
<hi>ſays,</hi> It is now the Seaſon for every Man to ſhew his Readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Courage, Love and Loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty to his Prince, who is the Care of Heaven, whom God long preſerve and ſtrengthen to overcome all his Enemies; and let us bleſs God who thus thought us worthy of ſo gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious a Prince, every way Great and Good, kind to us to the utmoſt of our Wiſhes, which paſt Ages have not known, and future will ſooner admire than believe, whoſe Wiſdom, and Juſtice, and Mercy, whoſe Munificence, Magnanimity, whoſe Bravery and Conduct has been ſhewed in 1000 Occaſions. A Prince whoſe Royal Vertues, and Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Merits intitle him to the Crown above all others, if he had not been born to it. <hi>See</hi> p. 27. <hi>of</hi> S. Rich<hi>'s Sermon, prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for</hi> Charles Broome, 1685.</note> roar, (our Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt Doctor in the Number) and call theſe few worthy Men (for the greateſt Number gives the Character) <hi>Forty one-Men,</hi> that the Nation was to look upon as Monſters, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volving their Country again under the Miſchief of that Age? Nay, ſuch Encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement was given by it, that upon that Foot it was the Patriots of our Country and Religion were deſtroyed; and the Nation ſo infatuated by the Principles a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove-mentioned, that Juries were found (I do not admire at Judges and Lawyers) to drain the Blood of their deareſt Friends; for thoſe muſt be called ſo, that fell Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices for their Country's Liberties. After this, what ſtood in <hi>Charles</hi> the Second's way? Did he not, like a Torrent, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve Corporations and find baſe ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vile Lawyers, of all Qualities, (ſome of which by their<note n="†" place="margin">Clergy-men.</note> means in this preſent Government, were choſe Members in Parliament, and there ſitting as Judges of their own Crimes, eſcaped unpuniſhed) to wreſt the Letter of the Law, ſhaking the very Baſis of our Ancient Government to ſerve his Turn, reſolving to have no Parliaments, (though he was never ſo long without one as his Father) till he got one of his own chuſing; and would, thus encouraged, have perfected the Ruin of theſe Nations. But Providence, in its ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret Wiſdom, thought he had gone far enough, and by his Death removed the Reins of Government into a Rider's Hand, that forced the willing Titts upon
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:42957:7"/>their Breath too far; then, almoſt jaded, 'twas, they kick'd to throw their Rider. Here 'twas the danger came in view, fooliſh Bigotry was diſcovered, and this dreaming Nation waked from its Lethargy, the flattering Churchmen ſaw their Intereſt, (their only God, without any reſpect to their Services done the Crown) in danger; and now began to urge for their Excuſe, in a thing plain as the Sun at Noon,<note n="*" place="margin">That King <hi>James</hi> was a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt.</note> 
               <hi>Who would have thought it?</hi> And proceeded to promiſe, [then in Danger]
<hi>Temper</hi> to their<note n="†" place="margin">The Bps Petition to K.
<hi>James;</hi> when they refuſed to read his Declaration. In all probabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity that Petition had the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of all the noted Clergy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men in
<hi>England.</hi> Of which if our Doctor and Mr. <hi>Long</hi> are Samples, how truly they in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended it, let the Reader judg.</note> 
               <hi>diſſenting Brethren,</hi> they for more than thirty Years together had had that diſtance with, the two Poles has not greater. Here any impartial Man may obſerve what ſet of Men <hi>theſe are,</hi> and what the generality of Mankind, thus influenced, muſt be. Theſe <hi>very Men</hi> ſtamped Characters upon their diſſenting Brethren; if true, would make Mankind ſtart at the<note n="|" place="margin">The Church-men in the laſt Reigns made no difference, though this Government does, between the Papiſts and Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterians; they aſſerted them like <hi>Sampſon</hi>'s Foxes, their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces contrary; but they were tied faſt together in the ſame miſchievous Deſign, of putting Church and Kingdom into Combuſtion and Flame. <hi>Joſ. Pleydell</hi>'s Sermon, <hi>p.</hi> 11. <hi>Aag.</hi> the 7th, 1681. printed for <hi>Joan. Broom,</hi> 1681.</note> ſight of them, yet can ſneak, cringe, and flatter the Men they made ſuch Villains of, to a Reconciliation, as ſoon as they wanted their Aſſiſtance; but being out of Danger, as ſoon forget all their Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes. They preach'd up <hi>Paſſive Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,</hi> &amp; for their Kings; and as ſoon as one touched them
<hi>to the quick, deſerted</hi> him, contrary to a thouſand Promiſes, made in the preſence of Heaven, of Loyalty and Obedience.<note place="margin">The Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of 1640.</note> The Villains theſe Men will not be compared to, were never ſuch, they never profeſſed Principles, and left them. The <hi>Gentleman,</hi> our conceited and huffing Pamphleteer, and his Reverend Crew, call <hi>Traitor,</hi> never forfei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted his Morals, his Honour, nor Opinion; he often <pb n="14" facs="tcp:42957:8"/>bravely look'd Danger in the Face to juſtify 'em; which Providence then and ſince has wonderfully appeared for; nor would he ever, having oppoſed thoſe De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns of
<hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt, be<note n="*" place="margin">He was offered Pardon by King <hi>Charles</hi> II. the Earldom of <hi>Eſſex,</hi> and an Eſtate anſwera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble when Lieutenant General in <hi>Ireland.</hi> They make part of his Crime his addreſſing his Books to Sir <hi>Ed. Seymor,</hi> chief Counſellor of State, known and owned by Mr. <hi>Long,</hi> (<hi>Pag.</hi> 4.) not write by him.</note> bribed into the Arbitrary Intereſt of
<hi>Charles</hi> the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, from the True Intereſt of his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, when an Exile, and from a plenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Eſtate bended low as the Ground. That the Doctor, Mr. <hi>Thomas Long,</hi> and the reſt of their Coat, ſhould rail at, and call this worthy Man <hi>Impious Regicide, Inſolent, Defier of the Laws,</hi> making barbarous Inſinuations upon all thoſe excuſing him, calling them by unheard-of Names, for which we want their Explanation, together with the Names of<note n="†" place="margin">Look Mr. <hi>Long</hi>'s Preface, and beginning of his Book.</note> 
               <hi>Villains, Common-Wealth's-men, Exploders of Monarchy and Epiſcopacy</hi> is no wonder, having always oppoſed the topping Points that miſled the late King; to which this Nation, if it happens, owes its Ruin. But at this time, when the Blind, at which theſe Men kick, is removed: Now we want all the Hands of faithful and brave Men, that the Inſinuations of theſe Grum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blers for Intereſt,<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Long</hi>'s Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter of the Clergy, <hi>Preface,</hi> pag. 2.</note> theſe <hi>ſtupor Mundi,</hi> ſhould influence the Parliament) a great Number of whoſe Members are as worthy Men as this Kingdom ever had, to Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſs to the King to iſſue out his Proclamation againſt a Gentleman, with a Reward for his Head, offering himſelf ſo ſeaſonably,<note place="margin">To ſerve in <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> where for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly he had been Lieute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant General.</note> that imploying him, had in all probability ſaved thouſands of Men, and Pounds, of whole Fidelity both to himſelf and theſe Nations, the King was abundantly ſatisfied, is ſo wonderful, it is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond all Belief and Example.</p>
            <p>Though I have been a little warm in this Paper, for which I think my ſelf very excuſable; yet Heaven is my Witneſs, though they ſeem not of my Opinion to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards <pb n="15" facs="tcp:42957:8"/>wards thoſe they call <hi>Common Wealth's-men,</hi> I intend nor deſire their Ruin, no not ſo much as Hurt to them; all I intend, is to convince, if not them, others, that
<hi>Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt</hi> is in their Thoughts more, at leaſt as much, as
<hi>Pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty;</hi> and that they are not ſo innocent as they unite to make themſelves; that their Church of <hi>England</hi> either had not that Purity in the laſt Reigns they boaſt of, or if it had, that they ceaſe to be the Profeſſors of it: and I would gladly be the Occaſion, when they find them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves no whiter than others, of their laying aſide Bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terneſs and ill Language, dividing their Power, (tho I am afraid, this Advice will be taken as our Saviour's was to the young Rich Man in the Goſpel) and to come to that Temper promiſed, thoſe, they think they cannot call worſe than
<hi>Common-Wealth's-men,</hi> and not endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, by that Name, to bring the Government upon their Backs, nor invite the Souldiers (for that muſt be the meaning of Mr. <hi>Long</hi> in his Book, <hi>pag.</hi> 4.) to cut their Throats: Such a Union will keep the Crown up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Heads of our preſent King and Queen; which Providence, as Mr. <hi>Long</hi> in the Preface, <hi>Pag.</hi>
4. of the ſaid Book, (the only thing to be granted him through it) by a Series of Miracles wonderfully has placed there, to make us, if we will our ſelves, a happy Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, maintain Monarchy upon its old Baſis, and the Laws in their proper Channels, keep out the old Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpenſing Judges from filling again the Seats at <hi>Weſtmin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter,</hi> to whom the Government and Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity will wonder at it, by the<note n="*" place="margin">The Power of theſe Men they ſtill depend upon; and after accuſed as falſe Interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of the Laws, and hazard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing three Kingdoms, for which they ſtand excepted in an Act of Indempnity, dare appear, and are countenanced at thoſe Bars they ſhould be brought to as the greateſt Criminals. The Lord Chief Juſtice <hi>Hales</hi> was almoſt prophetick in his Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, That there was more danger of introducing Arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary Power into theſe Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, by the Red-Coats in <hi>Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minſter-Hall,</hi> than by thoſe without.</note> Wiles of the old True-paced Church-of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi>-Men, has been too favourable to; 'twill break the Hearts of your Old and New Arbitrary Men, who expect to enter <pb n="16" facs="tcp:42957:9"/>at the Breach our eloquent Doctor and Mr. <hi>Long</hi> are unwarily making, defeat <hi>Rome</hi> and <hi>France,</hi> and may contribute much to the ſtopping of that Iſſue of Blood through Chriſtendom. Which that God of his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite Mercy may grant, with all Proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity to our preſent King and Queen, is the Prayer of one of thoſe <hi>Common-Wealth's-men</hi> our <hi>Doctor</hi> and Mr. <hi>Long</hi> would have the Nation frighted at: and I am ſure 'twas the Prayer of that worthy Man they gave ſuch bad Language to, his dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing words affirm it; for almoſt his laſt were Wiſhes for the Good of
<hi>England,</hi> and Peace of Chriſtendom: and all the Concern upon him was, that he had not the Honour of having his Eyes cloſed in averting the Eminent Hazards he ſenſibly perceived too much threatned his Country. He died in
<hi>October</hi> laſt 1692, lamented and commended by all that knew him.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:42957:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
